<chapter id="features.main">
  <title>How to configure and use the Phorum Features</title>

  <section id="features.vroots">
    <title>Virtual Roots</title>
    <section id="features.vroots.intro">
      <title>What are Virtual Roots?</title>
    <para>
      Virtual Roots allow you to run "a phorum inside a phorum".
      It makes the selected folder to the "root folder" of all forums and folders below it which means that the "forum-list" links go as far up as to this folder and searches for "all forums"
      are limited to forums in this virtual root. The announcement-module has also functions to use a different forum per virtual root for the announcements.
      On the other hand, the administration-page is about all the forums/folders and users are valid about all forums (in all virtual roots) in the installation.
      </para>
    </section>
     <section id="features.vroots.howto">
       <title>How do I create a virtual root?</title>
       <para>
      To create a virtual root just create a folder and select the checkbox "Virtual Root for descending forums/folders" for this folder.
      From now on every folder or forum below this folder will be contained in this virtual root.
       </para>
       </section>
  </section>

  <section id="features.modules">
    <title>Phorum Modules</title>
    
    <section id="features.modules.intro">
      <title>What are Phorum Modules?</title>
      <para>
        Modules are (often) small extensions to Phorum-functionality without sacrificing performance of the Phorum-core.
        You can install them if needed for using their functionalities.<sbr/>
        Take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.phorum.org/development/wiki/ListOfModules">Modules-List</ulink> to see the currently available modules.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="features.modules.installation">
      <title>How do I install a module?</title>
      <para>
        All modules are installed inside the subdirectory "mods" of your
        Phorum installation directory. There are two types of modules:
        single file and multi file modules.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Single file modules
            <para>
              Single file modules consist of a single php-file containing also the description and hook-names.
              These kind of modules can't have a settings-page.<sbr/>
              You install a single file module by simply dropping its php-file into the mods directory and enabling it in the administration pages.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Multi file modules
            <para>
              Multi file modules consist of at least a directory with a php-file named the same as the directory and an info.txt-file.
              Additionally for a settings-page there needs to be a settings.php. Beside these standard-files there can be all kind of
              files and directories used for the module's functions.<sbr/>
              You install a multi-file module by copying the whole directory (preserving its directory structure) into the mods-directory
              and enabling it in the admin.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  

</chapter>
