<chapter>
  <title>Upgrading instructions</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      This section describes the Phorum upgrading process. 
      We differentiate between three types of upgrades:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="upgrade.minor"/><sbr/>
          These are upgrades where only the last number in the
          Phorum version is raised (e.g. 5.2.1 to 5.2.2).
          These upgrades are mostly for implementing (security)
          bugfixes and minor enhancements that do not require any
          template and/or database changes.<sbr/>
          <sbr/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="upgrade.major"/><sbr/>
          These are upgrades where the second number in the Phorum
          version is raised (e.g. 5.1.10 to 5.2.2). These are upgrades
          where large new features are implemented. These upgrades
          will always require database and template changes.<sbr/>
          <sbr/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="upgrade.legacy"/><sbr/>
          These are upgrades where also the first number in the
          Phorum version is raised (e.g. 3.4.8 to 5.2.2).
          Now and then, the Phorum team starts with a version of Phorum
          that is built from the ground up, to implement all the new
          insights and ideas that are gathered while building the previous
          version. Since completely new code is generated, the version
          number is raised in full. These upgrades will always require
          a full database and site layout conversion, which might implicate
          a lot of manual work.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrade.minor" xreflabel="Minor upgrades">
    <title>Minor upgrades</title>
    <para>
      When doing a minor upgrade (e.g. 5.2.1 to 5.2.2), the upgrading
      process will preserve all of your active settings and modules. It
      will however overwrite hacks to the code and any changes that you
      have made to the default template in the directory
      <filename>{phorum dir}/templates/default</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This section will describe the steps for a minor upgrade.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrade.major" xreflabel="Major upgrades">
    <title>Major upgrades</title>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrade.legacy" xreflabel="Legacy upgrades">
    <title>Legacy upgrades</title>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Support</title>
    <para>
      <remark>TODO: Link to FAQ</remark>
      If you have questions about installing Phorum which
      are not answered by this manual, then please visit the website
      &www.phorum.org; and ask the development team for help in the support
      forum.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
